Guide to the Sylvester Manor Archive 1649-1996 MSS 208
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Record Group II: L'Hommedieu Family
  - Series B: Ezra L'Hommedieu
    - Subseries 8: Upstate New York Land Materials
      - Plattsburgh land: correspondence from Henry Delord, certificate for land, memo re land sale, 1786-1810 (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - Herkimer and Montgomery Counties, Danube, Minden and Canajoharie, 1793-1810 (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence re land near Plattsburgh with Joseph Bourn, Seth Sherry and Henry Delord, 1805-1810 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - Broome County, Randolph, 1789, 1794, 1807-1811 (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence re Steuben land from Joseph Montague, John L. Gardiner, Jacob Crams, 1790-1811 (Box 27, Folder 7)
      - Lands near Plattsburgh, Bourn, Cochran, Delord, 1804-1811 (Box 27, Folder 8)
      - Chemung, Mohawk River, 1786, 1789-1790, 1799, 1812 (Box 27, Folder 9)
      - Broome County, Chenango, 1791, 1807-1812 (Box 27, Folder 10)
      - Brookfield, Sangerfield, 1806-1807, 1810-1813 (Box 27, Folder 11)
      - Redfield notes and receipts, 1800-1809, 1813 (Box 27, Folder 12)
      - Redfield, Oswago River, Thichland (?), 1795-1814 (Box 27, Folder 13)
      - Upstate New York land - all areas, 1807, 1810-1811, 1817, undated (Box 27, Folder 14)
      - Contract - Sylvester Dering and Mary C. L'Hommedieu with Stephen Brook, for land in Redfield, 1819 (Box 27, Folder 16)
      - Steuben, 20 Townships, 1800-1819 (Box 27, Folder 17)
      - Twenty Townships [contains undated copy of Southold deed, 1712), circa 1807-1819 (Box 27, Folder 18)
      - Twenty Townships, circa 1797-1820 (Box 27, Folder 19)
      - Montgomery County, South of Mohawk River, John Taylor, 1784, 1789, 1810-1811, 1824 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - Plattsburgh, Lake Champlain, Clinton County, Peru, 1789-1824 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - Bonds, mortgages and contracts relating to Redfield settlement, 1800-1808, 1819-1824 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - Windsor County, Randolph, 1807-1825 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Randolph, Windsor, 1811-1825 (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - Redfield account book, circa 1828 (Box 28, Folder 6)
      - Receipts and accounts on payments and taxes for upstate land, 1806-1829 (Box 28, Folder 7)
      - Redfield, taxes for all areas, 1809, 1820-1827, 1830 (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - Taxes for all areas, Redfield [includes power of attorney of Mary C. L'Hommedieu to Samuel Gardiner, 1824, 1830, undated (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - Chenango, Redfield, Brookfield, Windsor, Rome, Black River, 1791-1806, 1832 (Box 28, Folder 10)
      - Taxes in town of Redfield, undated (Box 28, Folder 11)
      - "Remarks mde on the lots in Township no. 12 on Salmon River", undated (Box 28, Folder 12)
      - Committee on petition for relief from taxes, undated (Box 28, Folder 13)
      - Proprietors of Redfield unsold acres, undated (Box 28, Folder 14)
      - Documents with "Salmon River Map" - descriptions of lots, circa 1809 (Box 28, Folder 15)
      - Notes of land of Webb, Booth and Corey, undated (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Subseries 9: Miscellaneous Materials
      - Culinary and Medicinal Recipes and Formulas, undated (Box 28, Folder 18)
      - Letter Wrappers (loose and unused), undated (Box 28, Folder 19)
      - Letter Wrapper "Letters 1795", undated (Box 28, Folder 20)
      - "Queen Elizabeth Lammantation" (poem), undated (Box 28, Folder 21)
      - Untitled Poem, undated (Box 28, Folder 22)
      - Agricultural Papers and Notes, 1797-1804, undated (Box 28, Folder 23)
      - List of Towns and Counties in New York, 1790 (Box 28, Folder 24)
      - Design of Ezra L'Hommedieu Memorial, undated (Box 28, Folder 25)
      - Copy of Tombstone Inscription [?] for Chastity L'Hommedieu, 1785 (Box 28, Folder 26)
      - Invitations and Card to Ezra L'Hommedieu from "Turkey Work Wallet", undated (Box 28, Folder 27)
      - "Vigor A talis fluit ut Flos Voris" by Nicoll Havens, undated (Box 28, Folder 28)
      - Poem by Robert Burns, 1786 (Box 28, Folder 29)
      - "A Chart of the Port of Sag Harbor", circa 1800 (Box 28, Folder 30)
  - Series C: Mary Catherine Havens L'Hommedieu
    Born to the prominent eastern Long Island Havens family, Mary Catherine Havens (1765-1843) became the second wife of Ezra L’Hommedieu in 1803 and gave birth to one daughter, Mary Catherine L’Hommedieu, in 1806.
    This series contains correspondence, primarily among relatives and close family friends, and legal and financial papers that dealt with the management of estate of Ezra L’Hommedieu.
    - Subseries 1: Correspondence
      - D. H. Barnes to Charles T. Dering, 1822 (Box 28, Folder 31)
      - to "Cousin" (unspecified), 1820-1823 (Box 28, Folder 32)
      - to Anna Dering, 1808, 1824 (Box 28, Folder 33)
      - to Anna Dering and Frances Dering, 1823 (Box 28, Folder 34)
      - Charles Thomas Dering re Ezra L'Hommedieu Estate, 1821-1824 (Box 28, Folder 35)
      - [Charles Thomas] Dering, 1824 (Box 28, Folder 36)
      - to Henry P. Dering, 1814 (Box 28, Folder 37)
      - to [Henry P. Dering], 1816 January 2 (Box 28, Folder 38)
        Enclosed with letter Frank S. Landers to Andrew Fiske 1963, Box 118 Folder 12.
      - to Nicoll H. Dering, 1822, 1837 (Box 28, Folder 39)
      - to Sarah F. Dering, 1819 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - S.D. Franklin to Sarah Dering, 1821 January 21 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - Renslieur Havens, 1811 (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - to Catherine M. Huntington, 1831 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - Ezra L'Hommedieu, 1804 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - to Anne C. Lynch and grandchildren, 1832 (Box 29, Folder 6)
      - Gloriana Skinner, 1788 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - John Taylor, undated (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Series D: Sylvester Dering
    Sylvester Dering (1758-1820) was an owner of Sylvester Manor and was extensively involved in the colonial militia during the American Revolution, where he attained the rank of General and saw action at the Battle of Oriskany in central New York state. His wife was Esther Sarah Havens, sister to Mary Catherine Havens, who married Ezra L’Hommedieu. Sylvester Dering was appointed as one of the executors of Ezra L’Hommedieu’s estate
    This series contains correspondence relating to the management of the Ezra L'Hommedieu estate and as they are the only records of Sylvester Dering’s in the collection, they have been placed with the Ezra L’Hommedieu materials.
    - Subseries 1: Correspondence
      - LeBaron Bradford, 1819-1820 (Box 30, Folder 8)
      - William R. Briggs, 1819 (Box 30, Folder 9)
      - Ebenezer W. Case, 1818 (Box 30, Folder 10)
      - Aaron Clark, 1818-1820 (Box 30, Folder 11)
      - Jonathan Havens, 1795 (Box 30, Folder 12)
      - John Horner, 1819 (Box 30, Folder 13)
      - Samuel Jackson, 1818 (Box 30, Folder 14)
      - Thomas Ledyard, 1814 April 1 (Box 30, Folder 15)
      - Mary C. Havens (L'Hommedieu), 1799, 1800, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 16)
      - Mary C. L'Hommedieu, 1814-1815 (Box 30, Folder 17)
      - Mary C. L'Hommedieu, 1815-1818 (Box 30, Folder 18)
      - Mary C. L'Hommedieu, 1819-1820 (Box 30, Folder 19)
      - Ichabod Morton, 1819-1820 (Box 30, Folder 20)
      - Ebenezer Skiff, 1820 August 9 (Box 30, Folder 21)
  - Series E: Thomas Lester
    Thomas Lester was a Southold attorney and politician, who was appointed in Ezra L’Hommedieu’s will as one of the executors of his estate.
    This series contains correspondence relating to the management of the Ezra L’Hommedieu estate after his death.
    - Subseries 1: Correspondence
      - Samuel Bigg, 1812 January 28 (Box 30, Folder 22)
      - Nathaniel Bourne, 1819 December 24 (Box 30, Folder 23)
      - Lebaron Bradford, 1819 (Box 30, Folder 24)
      - Daniel Brown, 1812 (Box 30, Folder 25)
      - Latham Burrows, 1811 March 10 (Box 30, Folder 26)
      - Nathaniel Conkling, 1814 (Box 30, Folder 27)
      - Victor Crook, 1812 April 5 (Box 30, Folder 28)
      - David Davis, 1812 October 12 (Box 30, Folder 29)
      - Charles Thomas Dering, 1813-1817 (Box 30, Folder 30)
      - Henry P. Dering, 1805, 1815 (Box 30, Folder 31)
      - Sylvester Dering, 1805, 1812-1816 (Box 30, Folder 32)
      - John Franks, 1811 (Box 30, Folder 33)
      - John Gardiner, 1812 (Box 30, Folder 34)
      - Mary C. L'Hommedieu (Gardiner), 1812, 1814 (Box 30, Folder 35)
      - Robert Smith Gardiner, 1811 December 12 (Box 30, Folder 36)
      - H. Gleston, 1812 (Box 30, Folder 37)
      - Augstus Griffin, 1812 October 31 (Box 30, Folder 38)
      - Mo E. Hart, 1812 December 12 (Box 30, Folder 39)
      - Charles H. Havens, 1812 (Box 30, Folder 40)
      - Gabriel Havens, 1812 December 16 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - Rensselaer Havens, 1813-1814 (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - Jesse Hedges, 1812 November 11 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - David Hempsted, 1812 June 18 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - S. Howell, 1812 August 13 (Box 31, Folder 5)
      - Richard Hudson to Thomas Lester, 1812 January 3 (Box 31, Folder 6)
      - John Ingraham, 1812 (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - Nathaniel Ingraham, 1813-1817 (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - John Isaacs, 1811 December 25 (Box 31, Folder 9)
      - Abel Jones, 1815 (Box 31, Folder 10)
      - Frederick King, 1812 (Box 31, Folder 11)
      - Ezra L'Hommedieu, 1807, 1811 (Box 31, Folder 12)
      - Mary C. L'Hommedieu, 1813 (Box 31, Folder 13)
      - Mary C. L'Hommedieu, 1813-1814 (Box 31, Folder 14)
      - Mary C. L'Hommedieu, 1814 (Box 31, Folder 15)
      - Mary C. L'Hommedieu, 1814-1815 (Box 31, Folder 16)
      - Mary C. L'Hommedieu, 1815-1816 (Box 31, Folder 17)
      - Samuel L'Hommedieu, 1811-1815 (Box 31, Folder 18)
      - H. M. Moore, 1812 May 31 (Box 31, Folder 19)
      - Ichabod Morton, 1819 February 11 (Box 31, Folder 20)
      - Elisha Mulford, 1812 October 24 (Box 31, Folder 21)
      - Wines Osborn, 1812 October 27 (Box 31, Folder 22)
      - Silvanus Overton, 1812 February 11 (Box 31, Folder 23)
      - Joel and Jonathan Post, 1812 January 14 (Box 31, Folder 24)
      - Nehemiah B. Prince, 1812 May 25 (Box 31, Folder 25)
      - Joanna Reeve and James Hendrickson, 1812 January 30 (Box 31, Folder 26)
      - Josiah Reeve, 1812 February 1 (Box 31, Folder 27)
      - Samuel B. Romaine, 1811-1812 (Box 31, Folder 28)
      - Matthew T. Russell, 1813 (Box 31, Folder 29)
      - Enoch Ryder, 1812 (Box 31, Folder 30)
      - E. Sage, 1811-1812 (Box 31, Folder 31)
      - E. Sage, 1812 (Box 31, Folder 32)
      - E. Sage, 1812 (Box 31, Folder 33)
      - Nathaniel Sanford, 1812 (Box 31, Folder 34)
      - Isaac Satterly, 1812 September 5 (Box 31, Folder 35)
      - Peter Schermerhor and sons, 1812 June 22 (Box 31, Folder 36)
      - John Scott to Thomas Lester, 1812 August 19 (Box 31, Folder 37)
      - Abraham Skinner, 1811-1812 (Box 31, Folder 38)
      - Cornelius Sleight, 1812 (Box 31, Folder 39)
      - David Smiths, 1812 February 12 (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - General John Smith 1 of 2, 1812 February - May (Box 32, Folder 2)
      - General John Smith 2 of 2, 1812 June - December (Box 32, Folder 3)
      - A. Spooner, 1812 September 7 (Box 32, Folder 4)
      - Jared Stors, 1812 December 18 (Box 32, Folder 5)
      - John Stors, 1814-1816 (Box 32, Folder 6)
      - George W. Strong, 1813 (Box 32, Folder 7)
      - Joseph Terry, 1812 (Box 32, Folder 8)
      - Benjamin F. Thompson, 1811-1813 (Box 32, Folder 9)
      - S. Topping, undated (Box 32, Folder 10)
      - Benjamin Tucker, 1813 (Box 32, Folder 11)
      - Rufus Tuthill, 1812 (Box 32, Folder 12)
      - William Udal, 1812 (Box 32, Folder 13)
      - David Webb, 1812 October 3 (Box 32, Folder 14)
      - E. Wickes, 1812 (Box 32, Folder 15)
      - Benjamin Wright, 1814 August 7 (Box 32, Folder 16)
  - L'Hommedieu: Oversize
    - Oversize Series A Subseries 1: Benjamin L'Hommedieu
      - Deed - Thomas Youngs to Benjamin L'Hommedieu (Sr) for Land in Southold, 1709 (Box 142, Folder 1)
      - Contract - Benjamin L'Hommedieu (Sr) to Benjamin L'Hommedieu, Jr for 1 Acre of Orchard, 1727 (Box 142, Folder 2)
      - Transfer of Land - Thomas Conkling to Mary Conkling, 1732 (Box 142, Folder 3)
      - Indenture - John L'Hommedieu to James Atkins for "Negro Fellow Named Jo", 1737 (Box 142, Folder 4)
      - Benjamin L'Hommedieu Account with Jon and Jonathan Simpson, 1752 (Box 142, Folder 5)
    - Oversize Series B Subseries 1: Correspondence
      - Timothy H. Bigelow, 1789 (Box 142, Folder 6)
      - Benjamin Bourn, 1801, undated (Box 142, Folder 7)
      - Nathaniel Bourn, 1806 (Box 142, Folder 8)
      - Samuel Broome, 1763-1764 (Box 142, Folder 9)
      - DeWitt Clinton, 1810 (Box 142, Folder 10)
      - George Clinton, 1783 (Box 142, Folder 11)
      - T. Daggett, 1791 (Box 142, Folder 12)
      - P. Fanning, 1784 (Box 142, Folder 13)
      - Nicholas Fish, Adjutant General to Colonel Phineas Fanning, 1786 (Box 142, Folder 14)
      - William Floyd, 1783 (Box 142, Folder 15)
      - David Gelston, 1780, 1783, 1790, 1804 (Box 142, Folder 16)
      - Jonathan N. Havens, 1792, 1796 (Box 142, Folder 17)
      - James A. Hilhouse, 1763 (Box 142, Folder 18)
      - to Thomas Jefferson, regarding Resolutions of the Society for the Promotion of Agriculture, Arts and Manufactures, 1802 (Box 142, Folder 19)
      - John Lamb, Maximus Willett, and Hugh Hughes, 1784 (Box 142, Folder 20)
      - James Livingston, 1784 (Box 142, Folder 21)
      - P. V. B. Livingston, 1784 (Box 142, Folder 22)
      - William Livingston, 1764 (Box 142, Folder 23)
      - Letter from Jedediah Morse (re Gazeteer of North America) used as letter wrapper, 1788 (Box 142, Folder 24)
      - Simon Pool, et al, 1792 (Box 142, Folder 25)
      - Gilbert Potter, undated (Box 142, Folder 26)
      - Elihu Hubbard Smith, 1792 (Box 142, Folder 27)
      - George Smith, 1792 (Box 142, Folder 28)
      - Benjamin F. Thompson, 1810 (Box 142, Folder 29)
      - Robert Troup ("About Negroes Imported with Settlers"), 1803 (Box 142, Folder 30)
      - James Vaill to Benjamin Vaill, 1810 (Box 142, Folder 31)
      - Geoge Whitefield to Thomas Dering, 1764 (Box 142, Folder 32)
    - Oversize Series B Subseries 2: Financial Documents and Papers
      - Accounts and Receipts, Notes Due to James McClure, 1755-1779 (Box 143, Folder 1)
      - Account for 3/32 Brigantine Marshall, in Account with David Gelston, 1783 (Box 143, Folder 2)
      - Halliock's Creditors Account List, undated (Box 143, Folder 3)
    - Oversize Series B Subseries 3: Legal Documents and Papers
      - Insurance Policy for Sloop Elizabeth, William Hubbard for Jonathan Vail, 1768 (Box 143, Folder 4)
      - Court of Common Pleas subpoena of Constant L'Hommedieu, 1773 (Box 153, Folder 1)
      - Deed for Land in Southold, 1725-1789 (Box 148, Folder 1)
      - Deed - Francis Nicoll to Ezra L'Hommedieu for Menantick, Shelter Island, 1793 (Box 148, Folder 2)
      - Indenture between Gulian and Cornelia Verplanck; and Ezra L'Hommedieu, 1795 (Box 155, Folder 1)
      - Appointment of Ezra L'Hommedieu as Commissioner to Examine Claims of the Stockbridge Indians by John Jay, Governor of New York, 1797 (Box 143, Folder 5)
      - Ezra L'Hommedieu Last Will and Testament, 1809 (Box 148, Folder 3)
      - Discharge of the Office of Clerk of Suffolk County, Signed by Daniel D. Tompkins, Governor, 1810 (Box 143, Folder 6)
      - Indenture between Thomas and Mary Dering; Thomas Lane and Benjamin Booth, 1767 (Map-case Map-case 4.B, Folder 12)
    - Oversize Series B Subseries 4: Court and Legal Case Documents
      - List of Articles of Mr. Peck's Venue and Costs on Settling Mr. Peck's Estate, 1769 (Box 143, Folder 7)
      - Copy of Last Will and Testament of Robert Hempsted, 1779 Februray (Box 143, Folder 8)
      - Deed - Nathaniel Young and Israel Halliock, for Land in Southold, 1784 (Box 143, Folder 9)
      - Indenture and Deed - Edward Livingston to John McNabb, 1798 (Box 143, Folder 10)
      - Indenture - Elias Foster and Herrick Rogers with Dischare Attached, 1798 March 15 (Box 143, Folder 11)
    - Oversize Series B Subseries 6: US Government Documents and Reports
      - Manifesto and Proclamation to the Members of Congress by the Earl of Carlisle, Sir Henry Clinton and William Earl, 1778 (Box 148, Folder 4)
      - An Account of the Receipts and Expenditures of the United States, for the Year 1792, 1794 (Box 143, Folder 12)
    - Oversize Series B Subseries 7: New York State Government Documents and Reports
      - Rules of the Court for the Trial of Impeachments and the Correction of Errors, 1786 (Box 143, Folder 13)
      - New York - Act Concerning Election of Representatives to Congress, 1789 (Box 143, Folder 14)
      - Petition of John Keese and Catharine Tillinghast to Legislature of New York, 1802 (Box 143, Folder 15)
      - Report - The Warlike Stores and Other Property Belonging to the State of New York, 1805 (Box 143, Folder 16)
      - Excerpt/Portion of Report of Committee on Issues in Ohio, Illinois and Detroit, undated (Box 143, Folder 17)
      - In the Court for the Trial of Impeachments and the Corrections of Errors, undated (Box 143, Folder 18)
      - In the Court for the Trial of Impeachments and the Correction of Errors - Jacob Cuyler et al v Daniel Braut et al, undated (Box 143, Folder 19)
    - Oversize Series B Subseries 8: Upstate New York Land Materials
      - Indenture - Ezra L'Hommedieu to William Dunn for sale of land in Tioga County, 1792 (Box 143, Folder 20)
      - Indenture - Ezra L'Hommedieu to William Dunn for sale of land in Tioga County, 1792 (Box 148, Folder 5)
      - Map of Land South of Mohawk River in Tryon County, 1782 (Box 148, Folder 13)
      - Land Patent - 1440 Acres in Tioga County, Adjoining the Town of Chemung, 1787 (Box 149, Folder 1)
      - Land Patent - Lot No. 11 in the Township of Randolph, 1787 (Box 149, Folder 2)
      - Land Patent - Lot No. 4 in the Township of Randolph, 1787 (Box 150, Folder 1)
      - Indenture for Land in Chenango, Map of Great Bend Susquehannah, 1787, undated (Box 148, Folder 15)
      - Deed and Map for Land in Montgomery County on the South Side of the Mohawk River, 1788, 1789 (Box 148, Folder 14)
      - Maps - Land in Montgomery County North of the Mohawk River; 20 Townships; Constables Purchase, containting Redfield, 1795, undated (Box 148, Folder 8)
      - Printed Maps - Northeast Part of the Town of Mexico; Oneida Reservation, 1796, undated (Box 148, Folder 6)
      - Documents Regarding Land in Lawrence's Patent in Montgomery and Herkemer Counties, 1784, 1807 (Box 148, Folder 11)
      - Documents Regardind Lands Near Plattsburg, 1787-1824 (Box 148, Folder 12)
      - Newspapers Listing Lands and Mortgages for Sale, 1827 (Box 148, Folder 17)
      - Maps - Brothertown; Fonda's Patent; Lands Lying on the West Side of Lake Champlain; Township #12, undated (Box 148, Folder 7)
      - Map of Streckland, or No. 12, undated (Box 148, Folder 9)
      - Map of Chenango, undated (Box 148, Folder 10)
      - Maps of Lots in 26 Townships, undated (Box 148, Folder 16)
      - Land Patent - Patent No. 23 in Herkemer County, 1792 (Box 150, Folder 2)
      - Maps and Survey of Land at Three Rivers Point, circa 1806 (Map-case Map-case 4.B, Folder 5)
      - Map of Lot #4 in the Randolph Patent, 1811 May (Box 143, Folder 22)
      - Map of Redfield, undated (Box 143, Folder 21)
      - Salmon River Map, undated (Map-case Map-case 4.B, Folder 6)
    - Oversize Series B Subseries 9: Miscellaneous
      - Certificate of Membership - Society for the Promotion of Agriculture, Arts and Manufactures, 1801 February 20 (Box 143, Folder 23)
      - Proposals for a Bank (used as a wrapper), undated (Box 143, Folder 24)
      - Poem "Venus" by Mr. Buel(?), undated (Box 143, Folder 25)
    - Oversize Series C Subseries 1: Mary L'Hommedieu Correspondence
      - John H. Cotton, 1816 (Box 143, Folder 26)
      - Jonathan Havens to Mary C. Havens, 1799 (Box 143, Folder 27)
      - Ezra L'Hommedieu, 1784 (Box 143, Folder 28)
    - Oversize Series C Subseries 2: Mary L'Hommedieu Financial and Legal
      - Will (unsigned) - Mary C. Havens L'Hommedieu, 1826 (Box 143, Folder 29)
    - Oversize Series D Subseries 1: Sylvester Dering
      - John Gardiner to Sylvester Dering, 1814 (Box 143, Folder 30)
    - Oversize Series E Subseries 1: Thomas Lester
      - Martin Van Buren, 1817 (Box 143, Folder 31)
      - Sylvester Dering to Thomas Lester, 1814 (Box 143, Folder 32)
      - E. Sage, 1812 (Box 143, Folder 33)
- Record Group III: Gardiner Family
  This record group consists primarily of the records of Samuel Gardiner, who practiced law in Suffolk County and New York. Materials include correspondence, extensive accounting records, a large volume of professional legal papers, political and religious manuscripts, and some published materials. A small number of Mary Catherine L’Hommedieu Gardiner’s documents are also included.
  - Series A: Samuel Smith Gardiner
    Samuel Smith Gardiner (1789-1859) was a member of the prominent and wealthy Gardiner family, who traced their ancestry to Lion Gardiner, who had settled Gardiner’s Island in 1639 as the first English settlement in New York. Samuel S. Gardiner was educated at Williams College in Massachusetts, and practiced law in Suffolk County and New York. He was one of the secretaries of the New York State Constitutional Convention of 1821, and member of the New York State Legislature from 1823-1824. He married Mary Catherine L’Hommedieu in 1823. The couple had three daughters, Mary L’Hommedieu Gardiner, Phebe Dayton Gardiner, and Frances Gardiner. In 1827, the Dering family was forced to place the Sylvester Manor estate at auction because of debt, and Samuel S. Gardiner purchased the manor house and 578 acres for $10,400.
    This series contains correspondence, detailed financial records and accounting books, personal and professional legal papers, government and political publications, a small number of newspapers, and some religious and political manuscripts. The series also contains a number of documents from the papers of David Gardiner.
    - Subseries 1: Correspondence
      - Stephen Allen, 1823 March 20 (Box 32, Folder 17)
      - P. Boise, 1858 (Box 32, Folder 18)
      - Daniel Brown, 1828, 1829 (Box 32, Folder 19)
      - Oliver Brown to Charles Dering, 1823 December 8 (Box 32, Folder 20)
      - W.P. Buffett, 1856 (Box 32, Folder 21)
      - James F. Cagswell, 1809-1810, 1815 (Box 32, Folder 22)
      - Ebenezer W. Case, 1823-1827 (Box 32, Folder 23)
      - G.H.H. Case, 1852 (Box 32, Folder 24)
      - Levi H. Clarke, 1817 (Box 32, Folder 25)
      - Levi H. Clarke, 1818 (Box 32, Folder 26)
      - Dewitt Clinton, 1815 (Box 32, Folder 27)
      - John A. Collier and Daniel Brown re properties upstate 1 of 2, 1822-1830, undated (Box 32, Folder 28)
      - John A. Collier and Daniel Brown re properties upstate 2 of 2, 1822-1830, undated (Box 32, Folder 29)
      - John Collier, August 14, 1832 (Box 32, Folder 30)
      - G.S. Copp, 1849 (Box 32, Folder 31)
      - Phineas Corey, 1824-1828 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - Jemina Davenport, undated (Box 33, Folder 2)
      - Abraham Dayton, 1823 April 22 (Box 33, Folder 3)
      - Jonathan Dayton, 1821-1829 (Box 33, Folder 4)
      - to Jonathan Dayton, 1827, 1828 (Box 33, Folder 5)
      - Ralph Dayton re copy of Montauk Indian and East Hampton agreement, 1850 (Box 33, Folder 6)
      - J.C. Derby, 1853 (Box 33, Folder 7)
      - Charles Thomas Dering, 1852 (Box 33, Folder 8)
      - Frances M. Dering, undated (Box 33, Folder 9)
      - N.H. Dering, 1825 February 18 (Box 33, Folder 10)
      - D.T. Dickinson to W.L.F. Warren, 1840 (Box 33, Folder 11)
      - N. Dyckman, 1825, 1838 (Box 33, Folder 12)
      - William Dyckman, 1828-1837 (Box 33, Folder 13)
      - William Dyckman, 1838-1849, undated (Box 33, Folder 14)
      - J.H. Edmitt (?), 1859 (Box 33, Folder 15)
      - Ogden Edwards, 1832-1833 (Box 33, Folder 16)
      - Ogden Edwards, 1834 (Box 33, Folder 17)